this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software
[Music]
welcome to software engineering radio
I'm your host action man Charlie my
guest today is Spencer Kimball and we're
going to talk about cockroach TB Spencer
is the CEO and co-founder of cockroach
labs a company formed to accelerate the
development of cockroach TB previously
Spencer worked for 15 years at various
companies including Square Google and a
couple of his own startups his
experience at each step along the way
convinced him of the need for a better
open-source database before his
professional career Spencer co-authored
the open-source camp photo editing
software while an undergraduate at UC
Berkeley Spencer welcome to the show
thank you all sure happy to be here so
let's get started
how do you describe cockroach TB well
it's a distributed resilient sequel
database it's probably the minimum
number of words that you can use it's as
resilience
why the name comes from exactly you know
they had for whatever reason government
likes to do strange research they had a
program at some point to measure the
effects of radiation on different living
organisms and it turned out that
cockroaches were pretty resilient to
radiation and said the joke was always
that after World War 3 they'd be the
last things surviving that's interesting
name so your expedience kind of
convinced you to build a new open-source
database so can you talk about the
motivations behind that yeah absolutely
in my entire career it's been I guess
since 97 when I graduated University
it's been a sort of alternating between
building applications and wanting more
from the database and then you know
working on various infrastructure to
support applications you know especially
to address the needs that I'd seen in my
previous iteration as an application
developer and it became
clear early on that databases were going
to be a major sticking point in my
career I remember taking a class at
Berkeley on databases and being I found
it interesting but it it was kind of
something that you do for extra credits
as opposed to something that was a true
passion but as soon as I got out in
industry and I think was my first
startup in the.com boom I started
working with Postgres and Oracle and it
became immediately apparent that these
things would need to be sharded for the
scale that we had so that was the first
experience that I had of a database not
having what it took to meet the
applications sort of business
requirements and it's a pretty painful
experience to shard a database for
anyone that's done it making sure can
attest to this when I went to Google in
2002 that was one of the very first
projects that I was on which was the
AdWords database back-end
so they were using my sequel and that
had originally started as obviously just
a single my sequel database and it got
too big for one and so they created two
of them and split up the customers that
were using Adwords between those two and
then that went to four which went to
eight and then after eight it started to
really have problems with just
scalability how many connections was
each database node having to service and
there were other problems like how do
you figure out where a customer is
across all of the different database
shards and you know that at the
beginning they kind of just queried all
the shards at once but once they were
kind of at 16 or 24 32 shards then the
number of queries coming in just to find
out where customers were when they're
trying to log in with an email address
was overloading the servers I mean I'm
just giving you the tip of the iceberg
and the number of problems that were
caused by that architecture but one way
to look at how problematic it was is
that it became an anti-pattern at Google
so somewhat of an outlaw to architecture
and they didn't get off it for a good 10
years until they moved to spanner
eventually and there was when I was
participating in the project there was
what they called the ads war room every
morning where people would try to stamp
out the fire
that had lit up overnight so it's just
this endless slog in order to make this
my sequel database in the sort of
application level sharding work properly
and what's interesting is that Facebook
has at a similar architecture as do many
of the other big tech companies because
it's very obvious right you can put some
customers on shard one someone shard to
just keep track of where they are and
you can scale to a billion customers
necessary on Facebook of course has
scaled the billions of customers and
they are using vast vast numbers of
these shards it makes Google's AdWords
program our deployment look pretty small
in fact so it's it's a very popular way
of doing things but that was a great
example of where database is just you
know in their original incarnation
didn't meet the needs of many businesses
and that's become of course even more
common in in 2020 than it was in 2002 so
at Google again I actually didn't just
do the backends in the database related
stuff I also worked on various
applications over that time and
eventually found my way into building
infrastructure for distributed file
storage and then when I left Google I
did a startup which was private photo
sharing so definitely on the application
side and that's where the idea of
cockroach showed up because we had seen
over ten years and I say we because it's
me and the same co-founders I have four
cockroach we left Google and we did this
startup and then we went to square
together would kind of been a traveling
as a pack for a long time but you know
we we came to a conclusion when we left
Google that the existing database
options and open source were pretty far
behind what Google had been aggressively
working towards with you know ambitious
research and development projects during
our tenure there and that inspired us
right because we saw what Google had had
kind of reached by 2012 which was the
first time that spanner was starting to
hit production we saw them build
BigTable before that we saw a big table
morph into Megastore we saw the early
you know attempts at finding the point
in the solution space was
eventually became spanner and all of
that was significantly more advanced
than what existed in the open source
world in 2012
so we tried looking at HBase we looked
at MongoDB we looked at react we looked
at Cassandra we looked at some of the
things that were in the public cloud and
eventually you know it was the same kind
of story as we examine each of those
options which was initially excitement
and then a bit of a letdown kind of went
into that trough of despair this isn't
really going to work doesn't have all
the things we need and that's where the
idea of cockroach DB was born so can we
build something in open source that we
could use for this project and that lots
of people could use for their projects
which has a lot of the same capabilities
and guarantees as the advanced databases
Google had been building you know it's
been particularly resilience scale and
even this idea that there exists
locality to data so you might have
customers in the EU and customers in the
US and you have to service them
differently and store their data
differently all of those ideas in one
single package that was open source
that's that was the manifesto and
cockroach is an example of our kind of
what I call it a slightly darker
interest in preference for names you
mentioned that we worked on the
that was paying homage to the pulp
fiction character of the same name which
was the top of mine in 1993 when we
started that project so you know
cockroach TB sounded pretty funny what's
actually even more funny is that
nowadays I'm explaining that to fortune
50 CIOs and CTOs
which is it's actually a pretty good
icebreaker but it's also a little
embarrassing we show up at one of these
glass paneled office receptions and have
to spell out your company name you
mentioned you evaluated MongoDB that was
something that was raising in popularity
not more but DB per se but just no
sequel systems that kind of promised a
scale not seen in relational databases
what was the problems with that
oh there's a lot to like about MongoDB
it unfortunately at that time it wasn't
as scalable as you might have expected
with a distributed architecture like it
had certainly had some some issues
around how that can how that worked in
practice I think the biggest issue
though that we had and it was it was a
pain point I was experienced at Google
as soon as BigTable came out which is in
2004 it was just immediately apparent
that that no sequel model without
transactions was going to be a difficult
hurdle for a lot of applications that
really did need transactions in order to
maintain correctness one of the big
lessons at Google and I think this is
just true everywhere nowadays but when
you have scale if something can go wrong
it absolutely will go wrong and will go
wrong quickly and it will metastasize
into a major problem so the the MongoDB
of 2012 and it's introduced transactions
in the years since but at that point it
felt like that architecture was going to
cause more problems than it would solve
for us so you know Cassandra had similar
deficiencies they also didn't have that
this is actually pretty much a feature
of no sequel not to have transactions in
those days now it's increasingly a
feature of no sequel systems I'll give
you an example fauna DB is one where
it's both in foundation DB was another
where was built from the ground up with
transactions and that I think is a
realization that no sequel was about
allowing elastic scalability and that
was it's big capability that was new to
the market but it gave up a lot of
things you might not like sequel right
but everyone likes transactions if
you're an application developer assuming
you know what they are and and that's
was one of the things they gave up early
on because you know it's complicated
difficult adds latency difficult to get
the model right it was essentially just
simpler to ignore that stuff and you can
build lots of interesting applications
that don't need transactions but what
you also realize is that
you might start not needing them but you
quickly find ways to introduce new
functionality that starts to break if
you don't have transactions so that was
Google's experience and Megastore
introduced basic transactions and the
spanner introduced very general-purpose
transactions and so that was one of the
big sticking points for us with no
sequel you know in 2012 we just come
from a world where transactions were you
know seen is a necessity so to exit
Google and find that there was a bunch
of open source stuff that kind of looked
the way Google looked in 2004 2005 was
it was a little bit depressing honestly
you mentioned one thing that you were
doing was partitioning or shard in your
databases so do you have transactions
across those partitions did you how did
you manage that D are you referring to
cartridge and not cockroach like just
historically was that a point of concern
that you wanted to have transactions
across your partitions yeah absolutely
and that was a big problem with the
AdWords system you know because it was
composed of multiple independent my
sequel databases you could within one
database have transactions and believe
me they did have transactions and that
was very important you know the the
problem was that they quickly found use
cases where they wanted to do
transactions across these shards and
what would that force them to do is make
other decisions architectural II so that
all the data they could ever do a
transaction between how to be on one
shard which didn't always work for
example some customers believe like eBay
that had so many ads on on AdWords they
wouldn't fit onto a single shard so they
without transactions that are
general-purpose
you inevitably if you're succeeding will
find ways that your models going to
break so that was definitely the
experience at AdWords and that wasn't
the only problem another examples sequel
gives you this amazing ability to ask
the database for data and it's sort of
declarative fashion instead of
imperative and the database is going to
use it smarts whatever it's got to go
fetch the data and combine it in is
efficient manner as its capable of but
that's only true for us you know within
a single shard you couldn't do queries
across these shards because these
databases didn't know about
each other and there was no sort of
centralized brain that could schedule
this work and have it be done
efficiently and that's essentially what
cockroach is it's that brain that uses a
lot of machines and moves the data
around them and schedules and optimizes
and so forth it is that thing that
didn't exist so what you have to do in a
case like google back in 2002 with this
AdWords system but you got to try to
build some of that in at the application
level but as much as you can on one
shard and then where you have to go
cross shards you have to do it as a
programmer as an application developer
which is difficult to get right and then
very difficult to maintain can you walk
us to what a cockroach DB deployment
looks like a cluster of nodes and how
does that do transactions let me just
start by saying I'll try to give you a
pretty high-level answer to that but
there are a lot of blog posts if you
search for cockroach DB and transactions
and distributed sequel and things that
will explain this in painstaking detail
and that you know that can be a really
interesting resource that people want to
find out more I did include that in the
show notes great so a little bit about
how you deploy cockroach basically we
tried to make it this is one of the
guiding design principles because it's
very different to Google and I didn't
like the way it worked at Google we try
to make cockroach so that there's a
single binary and it's symmetric so all
the nodes run exactly the same binary
with nearly identical command line
parameters and you only kind of be only
differ where you say you know this node
is on this particular rack and you sort
of specify the location of the node so
that is different between nodes but
otherwise it's identical
and then those nodes work together
without any kind of external
dependencies so they don't require
zookeeper to run and require a
distributed file system underneath them
they don't require access to external
things like a timekeeping service so
that allows that symmetric architecture
allows for an easier deployment story
especially in you know with different
tools like there was the Mesa sphere
stuff which is DCOs
you know that's a very different
environment from running something on
kubernetes as an example but all of
these are things where our customers
want to run
or just run it on bare metal so you know
just to give you a practical explanation
you can start a single cockroach node
and you basically tell it to initialize
itself and then when you want to create
the next node you simply point it at the
first node that's all you have to do and
then they'll begin to self organize and
replicate data and move data between
them so that it's equalized in terms of
the capacity between the two nodes if
you add a third they need to talk to
either of the two existing to be out of
fourth similarly any of the three
existing and so on so you can even grow
it that way and you can also
decommission nodes and shrink a cluster
as necessary and it will heal the you
know we up replicate the pieces of data
that were stored on the the node that's
been decommissioned so that you're
always maintaining the sort of desired
number of additional replicas of any
particular piece of data so that's I
sorta had the deployment works it's
supposed to be very automated very
straightforward and simple or
automatable maybe is the right word but
once it's running it automates
everything itself or everything that it
can transactions there's a fairly
involved model for how they work and
this is something that again you know
it's best to refer to some of these blog
posts because the model has gotten
incredibly sophisticated it started as
an amalgamation of different transaction
algorithms from research papers and it's
since morphed into something even more
particular to cockroaches use case I'll
give you a little bit of a detail about
that in a second it basically it's a
distributed transaction model and the
goal with these things is is that when
something goes wrong in the system let's
say that you know the transaction begins
and you modify you read a bunch of data
from different nodes and you modify data
which is all existing on different nodes
all those things are being touched when
you abort that transaction all of those
changes should be seen as intermediate
they should all go away
nothing should be left if anything
happens concurrently while the
transactions underway that concurrent
execution or worker reader or writer
whatever it is won't see anything that's
still in an indeterminate state that the
transaction is started when you commit
the transaction
all of that data it needs to be come
committed and available and viewable at
the same time it needs to be a sort of
virtual simultaneity so that's that's
the the heavy lift that this transaction
model is doing there's you know a lot of
particular details in terms of how it
actually works but to give you an idea
of where we've kind of been pushing the
state of the art we've recently you know
in the last four years been looking at
lots of use cases that have to do with
storing data in different data centers
in different regions so like East Coast
West Coast United States even on
different continents and this is often
something that customers might want in
terms of keeping the latency low for a
user in Australia for example or
complying with data sovereignty
regulations like GDP are where can you
actually legally store the data or where
does the user want you to store their
data so all of those considerations make
it so that you actually can put data you
know far away geographically such that
even you know even if you were beaming a
light through vacuum in order to send a
signal you'd still have hundreds of
milliseconds of latency and it's more
than that sometimes through you know
these communication networks so how do
you make a transactional model that
looks like sequel our sequels work in
that environment that has geographical
agencies that's a pretty difficult
problem if you do it in a naive fashion
which would I think fairly accurately
describe our original approach to the
transaction model those latencies let's
say it's a hundred and fifty
milliseconds between two nodes and
they're interacting in this transaction
and you're doing a bunch of different
writes in the naive way those 150
millisecond latency Zaid up serially so
if you did ten writes you'd have 1.5
seconds which is horrific kinds of
latency is it's not tenable for building
an application and so what we had to do
is say are there ways to change how that
works in practice and we've been able to
get an entire distributed transaction
even with 150 millisecond latency
instead of taking 1.5 seconds for those
10 writes plus another 150 for what's
called the sort of
second phase of the distributed
transaction to do the commit to be about
one point six five seconds we're able to
get that down to exactly 150
milliseconds so it's you know we do
something called pipelining which is
somewhat obvious sort of response and
then there's a very non obvious part of
that which something called parallel
commits which sort of hides the latency
on that second phase of the transaction
so the actual application that's doing
the transaction only sees a hundred and
fifty milliseconds of latency before
it's guaranteed that everything's
committed globally in fact so that's it
that's an amazing result and that's the
result of you know years now of work on
this transaction model but you can kind
of see how you know it's one thing to go
from no sequel to something like no
sequel transactions that's that's a
pretty difficult step on its own which
is why it took so long for example from
MongoDB to get transaction
Cassandra does even have transactions
then the the follow-on work that we're
now contending with is this realization
that the you know everything's global
nowadays and customers actually are and
in fact their data sometimes needs to be
domiciled and even different continents
so how can you still do transactions in
a way that still works and so that's
some of the novel stuff that we're
working on now okay let's say you have a
single table rate so does geographic
distribution actually show up latency in
within a single node that is let's say I
have a single node with some part of the
data and one update something do I see
geographical agencies in working in the
context of a single node well if you
just have a single node in a cockroach
cluster which is you know obviously
something that you could do it won't
have any Geographic latency because you
know it's just one knows it's only
sitting in a single location so what's
very common is it's kind of like the
right way to think of cockroach is to
think about the different stages of
sophistication that you'd go through as
a start-up than growing into a bigger
and bigger company so as a start-up you
might think that well we're probably
just going to have you know it's about
standing this thing up making the
application work getting some initial
users and failing fast in that
particular case you probably have
you know one day one or three nodes of
cockroach and a single availabilities on
that it's nice to have three nodes of
cockroach because you have three copies
you can lose one of the nodes sometimes
that happens you know AWS will sometimes
lose nodes of course from hardware
failures or they'll relocate your VM or
let's shut it down you you want
cockroach to go to survive even when
it's in a single data center and you may
actually want to scale it that way and
that's sort of the next level of
sophistication so now you've proved out
your model you're getting lots of users
you might still be in the same
availability zone and now you say okay
we don't want just three nodes we want
to have ten nodes and we can service you
know a lot more requests in terms of the
reads and the read and write throughput
that's necessary to run our application
for now five hundred thousand users or
something like that and then what
happens is your business whatever it is
starts to become somewhat
mission-critical maybe customers are
paying you or your customers your SAS
business and your customers are other
companies and they have SLA is you have
to meet terms of uptime at that point
that's where cockroach really starts to
come into its own and you actually do
spread the nodes out geographically so
you potentially put them in three
availability zones all in the same
region as an example so it's very fast
latency between these availability zones
you're talking like less than ten
milliseconds but now you can lose a data
center and there's always two additional
replicas and two other data centers and
together they're able to have the single
source of truth like the most recent
data that's been written and then
finally you kind of move into this level
of sophistication where you start to
have customers outside of the United
States or you start to really care about
the latency for customers outside the
United States you might have had them
the whole time but they're always
jumping over to Virginia or something
like that from Australia which hasn't
been a good experience so now you're a
company like hey we want to build
something looks like Facebook where
everything feels local no matter where
you are so in that particular case
you're actually now using data centers
all over the world and replicating
sometimes globally sometimes you're
replicating only in the EU for an EU
users data basically there's a lot of
different kinds of architectures you can
build with cockroach
very flexible as you grow through these
levels of sophistication but that should
give you a little bit of perspective on
what the geographical agencies actually
are and what they mean so you know if if
you really care about latency you know
on any Geographic latency at all then
you put all your things in a single data
center which works fine but if you
decide that you want to have additional
resilience to lose a data center you
have to introduce some latency that's
the trade-off and it's very fundamental
like if you don't want to put all your
things in one data center in fact you
might want to keep them like a hundred
kilometers apart which i think is a
banking regulation there's a reason for
that right because two data centers that
are right next to each other they could
be hit by the same earthquake or tsunami
or you know you know whatever natural
disaster a meteor strike or a fire or
something that knocks out like the the
trunk that they're both using for fiber
optics I mean some backhoe in a
construction project like all kinds of
these random things happen so you do
want to keep your replicas
geographically far enough away that then
what are called non-correlated failure
domains but of course that introduces
latency so there's always a question of
how much latency is okay and it that
depends on the use case it turns out
that you know even replicating across
the United States and let's say you have
a high-value use case and I believe this
is true of Google's AdWords system at
least it was you know some number of
years ago they actually had five
replicas across the United States I'm
pretty sure across three three different
US power grids and what with a system
like spanner which is cockroach is very
similar to you can lose two out of those
five replicas as long as you've got
three remaining so three those data
centers across the u.s. you have total
uptime so it's it's it's really cool
system because this is actually not
something that never happens where you
put one data center into a plan
maintenance so you take it down and then
you have an unplanned outage in one of
your remaining four but you still have
complete business continuity in that
case so it's it's a it's a pretty robust
resilient architecture and in that case
your latency is usually going to be
about thirty five milliseconds to do a
transaction and you know for
people that are used to building
applications that talk to the database
where the two are literally machines on
the same rack 35 milliseconds seems like
a long time to wait but the reality is
that for the end and latency that
matters to the end-user you really want
to get things under 100 milliseconds and
in people that worry a lot about the 35
milliseconds of latency to do a
transaction often aren't really looking
at the end and latency that their
service typically does have because you
know typically for a user to get from
their cell phone to the cell tower onto
the backbone into the data center you
know through the app server into the
database and then all the way back out
through those layers and god forbid it's
like a micro services architecture
that's you know doing all these things
serially and in any case these things
can add up and usually at the 35
milliseconds is a bit of a rounding
error in terms of the total length of
time that a user's waiting which these
days is often anywhere from like about
500 milliseconds to a second and a half
the only companies that have really
gotten that down are companies like
Facebook and Netflix and Google and
Apple that have built these you know
global data architectures and worry
about that end-to-end latency but that's
kind of where you know people get a
little scared of the idea of geographic
latency but it's it's really important
to look at the bigger picture which is
what's my end-to-end late so you want to
click a button in this mobile app to
when something happens on the screen
after it's interacted with the backend
and and that is that's the sort of
controlling critical path and then you
know the beauty of having something that
takes 35 milliseconds because it's
replicating to five data centers across
the United States does that thing is
never going to go down all right so it's
it's everything is about trade-offs in
computer science and there's in like
this is the sort of next generation of
databases which is saying okay this
isn't gonna happen in two milliseconds
you can you can make it work that way
you can run in one data center but
that's not what you want for your
business
in fact it's it's a horrible story for
latency when you have to millisecond
transactions because your database and
your application server are right
together when the users coming from
Australia and your application server
micro-services whatever and your
database are both in data center in
Virginia all right in that case that
user is probably going to have at least
a
second of latency to get end-to-end on
their service because they have to jump
all the way across the globe there just
doesn't matter that you're getting two
milliseconds to your database right so
there's like there's a there's a
perspective shift which is necessary
when you're thinking about these
next-generation platforms and
architectures and I'll tell you this is
going to become really top of mind for
developers because what's coming down
the pipe is 5g and 5g is gonna make it
so that the latency that's sort of
experienced through your mobile device
can feel instantaneous if the service
that it's accessing or the application
that you're using is you know within the
same region that the user is in if that
all works well then you can give them an
incredible experience like the way it
feels when you type on your computer and
you see things immediately pop up and
you know the letters pop up as you type
like if that didn't happen in less than
100 milliseconds
it would feel weird and actually would
be quite discombobulating so you know
that's that's how it feels that the
keyboard and you know people pretty much
solve that problem it happens in less
than 100 milliseconds right now the the
average user is used it's very much
trained to expect a really slow
experience when they're online on a
mobile device but as that begins to
change applications that don't change
with the times are gonna feel somewhat
antiquated you mentioned that developers
are going to start seeing this they're
used to seeing a single node database
and one thing I noticed was that
cockroach is compatible with Postgres
can you talk about that yes you know we
early on decided that backup just one
one maybe a couple months earlier I'd
been working on a designed argument for
cockroach and that design document got
fairly wide circulation I don't know
exactly how it got shared around but it
ended up on Hacker News and people are
pretty interested in it that early
version it talked a lot about what we're
talking about right now it did not talk
about sequel and in fact I done I'm not
exactly the world's expert on sequel to
put it mildly
and I wasn't super interested in it but
I did realize that sequel was the it's
called the lingua franca of database
systems and was heavily in use
in most of the world's big companies so
when we actually started the company
cockroach labs in order to accelerate
the development of cockroach DB which
was just a github project at that point
time we came to the very early
conclusion that okay great we've been
thinking about a distributed
transactional key value type no sequel
database but in fact it's just another
layer to add sequel and sequel is a
massive market like we're gonna make
this a commercial entity and we
eventually want companies to pay us we
should think about what those companies
are actually using and while no sequel
at that point in time was you know very
popular and it seemed like it was for a
lot of people okay we don't even need
sequel anymore I that that proved to be
a bit of a head-fake and I think we just
had a little bit of luck and a little
bit of insight that you know listen we
the luck was probably mostly that we've
been working at Google for a decade
before and we'd seen them go through the
exact cycle that the bigger ecosystem
was going through in 2012 they'd gone
through it in 2004 and they realized
okay these no sequel systems need more
they're not good enough and eventually
it came back around a sequel and that's
what Google uses now so it was just you
just realized that no sequel was really
about scale and then they started adding
things piece by piece transactions first
and then other capabilities and came
back to the realization that you would
need sequel so as a little long-winded
sorry but you know we we early on
decided okay sequel is the right thing
for us and you know what flavors should
it be and we I think we originally
talked to Google about doing some sort
of open sequel thing that could be
shared between spanner and Google but it
you know we just had different timelines
between the two companies and and so
that didn't really work out it wasn't
good enough communication and Postgres
is what we settled on we just you know
it's like what you don't why would you
create your own dialect right in this
day and age when there's so much usage
between my sequel and Postgres and
oracle couldn't really do Oracle's like
we didn't think it was the right thing
for an open-source database also Oracle
is a very you know their company that
likes to use the legal system
so we didn't really want to get caught
in those those gears so Postgres seemed
to be the more considered approach to
sequel and my sequel is more suited the
pants and they seem to be the less
mistakes in Postgres so we opted for
four trying to get reasonably compatible
Postgres and part of the thinking there
wasn't just okay people know it's large
number of developers no Postgres already
and they know the dialect was also we
wanted to work with the tools in the
ecosystem there's a lot of those and it
was you know quite important to make
sure that we integrated with as many as
we could most developers I'm sure people
listening to this show very much
included and including myself you know
having to code directly through JDBC
ODBC or whatever you're using you know
it's not not so pretty because
especially the results you get back from
the database are in a particularly
annoying format to then convert into the
sorts of objects or structures that
you're using in whatever programming
language is your choice so ORM x' and
things like that are just critical time
savers you know usually they're Auto
generating code that just takes care of
all of that connective tissue and busy
work so it's a huge win and you know
building our own drivers and making them
work with all the tools if we had
something that didn't look like Postgres
be possible but just another huge amount
of work that we thought you know what
let's let's figure back on what Postgres
has done right if i'm using Postgres i'm
probably used to say expecting something
from a single node database but here
cockroach is kind of like a distributed
database of sort is there like eventual
consistency is there a difference in how
I can expect what is visible what's not
visible the in cockroach there's no
eventual consistency and every node
looks like the whole database so if you
if you're talking to one out of 100
nodes and you're asking for data that
know most certainly won't have the data
you're looking for unless you can plan
it so I want to put a big caveat on that
you can do a lot of things with
cockroach to make things very very
efficient if you know what you're doing
and you have a real need for it but in
the general purpose case every
we'll do forwarding and so forth to
other nodes to find the data and this is
true in MongoDB and is true and
cassandra and it's you know all of these
distributed systems try to make the
lives easier for application developers
that you don't want to have to know
exactly what node to connect to to get a
particular piece of data that's just
that's too inefficient too difficult so
yeah I mean cockroach it's the way the
thing about it is every node is a
gateway into the larger database that
will serve you a consistent view of the
database interesting just to I don't
know that's something you mentioned
earlier was that for compliance reasons
people may want to keep data within a
single geographic region say gdpr
or something is that something that you
define when I create a table for example
say this range of users should always be
in this continent yes that's exactly
right
it's a there's a feature in Oracle and
Postgres and believe my sequel has it
too sequel server
it's called partitioning table
partitioning and you can specify a
column that you'd like to partition the
data on in a monolithic system like
those others I just mentioned you
usually you use partitioning in order to
put certain kinds of data on less
expensive disk drives for example on the
same database server or to make it so
that the most recent data is on its own
partition so you can easily back it up
and restore it without having the full
archive worth of data to constantly
backup so partitions been around for a
long time what we introduced is a sort
of new twist on it which is called geo
partitioning and you can take those same
table partitions and you can assign
constraints to them so I just give you a
concrete example let's say that in your
data model you include a column and in
this table they want a partition which
is region maybe it contains strings like
EU de for Germany and EU fr for France
and us NY for New York you can say that
for anything that starts with us the
partitions should be you know replicated
only within data centers in the US you
might say for any US states that are
east of the mason-dixon line that they
should be replicated to the three data
centers that
you have on the East Coast and similarly
for West Coast and so forth and
similarly in the EU you can do the same
thing you might actually also say well
Germany
this is PII financial ledger or
something like that in Germany you might
have to keep all of those replicas only
in Germany it's like a more specific
regulation than GDP are and you in that
particular case would say anything that
has you de and that column any customer
data that's German in other words should
be replicated only within Germany maybe
you've only got one data center in
Germany all three replicas are gonna be
in that one data center and that's just
what you're gonna do is it's not super
resilient but you're maintaining your
legal responsibilities according to
German law in the broader context can
you talk about what happens in the
presence of failures and partitions you
know let's talk about say cap there's a
partition is cockroach DB available is
it consistent where do you stand
yeah well it's consistent of course
available is is an interesting word when
you talk about the cap down it doesn't
mean what people think available means
available when you talk to most people
they're talking about high availability
and how many 9s do we have and cockroach
is highly available in the sense that
you know it has multiple replicas
there's a consensus algorithm that does
the replication which maintains
consistency as long as a majority of
your replicas are available I don't
wanna use that word again let's just say
reachable they're communicating then
you're able to access your data read and
write it and so forth and you can you
can increase the number of replicas and
the number of data centers and as I
mentioned before how far apart the data
centers are for example in control how
many nines you get I mean you can make
your nines go out arbitrarily far so if
you have five replicas across five data
centers and they all have the same
probability of failure that's better
than three well because across three
data centers if you have seven replicas
across seven or I'll put the data
centers that's even better than the five
right and so on and so forth so you can
control exactly what your SLA guarantees
are in terms of what would I call like
estimated probability of availability of
the data so that's the highly available
thing that people actually care about in
practice let me talk about available in
the cap theorem it means that a node is
reachable and on and if that's true it
should be able to serve the data that it
has so in other words it's sort of like
in any note off on their own and in a
system that is for example ap in the cap
theorem that note on its own no problem
it can serve the information so that's
why it's not consistent because it's it
can kind of go AWOL and be split brain
or whatever you want to call it and
serve up super old information or
information that hasn't been
corroborated by the other replicas so
it's you know maybe tentative
information so that's that's the AP side
I'm cockroach by contrast you must have
a majority of the replicas so it
maintains consistency through that
mechanism but what it means is that if
you don't have a majority let's just
take three replicas so you've only got
one replica left that replicas available
and by the definition of available and
so in an AP system that replicas could
just give you the data which could be
wrong I encourage if you've just got one
out of three nodes it can't tell you the
data it will refuse to because it hasn't
has no way of knowing that it has the
right data when it can't get consensus
so yeah I mean it's it's a I think it's
a very common misconception when you
talk about cap to believe that a system
that maintains consistency like
cockroach can't be highly available I
mean nothing's further from the truth
the whole point of cockroach is that it
is highly available it simply means that
singular you know minority nodes in
cockroach and that can't get consensus
they can't operate independently well
initially you mentioned that cockroaches
like a single deployment where you know
you have a single binary that's common
across all data centers or all regions
how do you go about upgrading your your
databases do you bring nodes down and
then rejoin the cluster die exactly if
you have a single node then you're not
gonna have you know a very seamless
upgrade process you have to take that
single node down and bring backup
there's no redundancy there with three
nodes it's very simple you know what you
do is a rolling restart and we have an
upgrade process that lets you you know
because as you can imagine as you have
successive major
versions there are things that change in
the underlying data model and so forth
so there's there's kind of a point of no
return if you migrate to indoor version
but what we do is we kind of allow that
to happen in two steps
so the first step is you might get
access to things that don't either
change the underlying data and you can
try all those things out run your system
and so forth
that so that it looks pretty much like
there's no incompatibilities with the
previous version but you're trying the
new version and then you kind of flip a
switch which commits you to the new
version and then you can start using the
newer features that might write data
that's not compatible with the old one
this allows you to go backwards there's
very important metering and upgrade
so with cockroach what you do like
practically in terms of the deployment
you have three nodes they're all in
version one let's say you take down node
one you can actually give it a command
that sort of drains the traffic off it
gracefully and then when that's
decommissioning is done you take it down
you start the new binary it starts back
up it joins the cluster now you've got
one out of three that's running version
two let's say and now you've got three
nodes again they all have the data
they're replicating and so forth you
know when you upgrade the version you
still keep the data that's all in that
node so it's not it's a fairly fast
process to put a new binary on there and
not usually it always is and then you do
it to the second node and you do it to
the third node now at this point you
have three nodes that are all version
two but they're not necessarily using
any non backwards compatible
functionality and that point you you
sort of flip the cluster wide thing and
you can only flip it when all the nodes
agree that they're at version 2 and then
that upgrades you to this sort of okay
now we're we're fully in version 2 and
we have all the features available in
version 2 let's talk a little bit about
the open source aspect of cockroach TB
one thing i noticed that is that extra
tenant golang so what led you to you
know make the choice and how has that
been for database development well
actually on balance we're very happy
with go it's performance is improved in
fact you know in the first three years
of cockroach every time a new version of
go came out we get like another 15%
performance it was pretty cool just kind
of get that for free and the garbage
collector works pretty well
the reality though is that garbage
collectors there they're a an
abstraction that you end up having to
to break if you're building something
like cockroach luckily you only have to
worry about the garbage collectors doing
and how many allocations you're creating
that are creating pressure on the
garbage collector let me to worry about
that in certain critical areas of your
code so typically what we do is we just
program normally and go and don't worry
about that stuff and then when we start
to really do performance optimization we
look at the allocations and we cut those
down in the critical path the critical
sections of the code basically and
that's been a very effective strategy
but fundamentally you are breaking the
abstraction like you shouldn't have to
worry about the garbage collector but
you you you you do and go but luckily
you can limit it to these small sections
rust by contrast which would be the
other language that I think if you
polled our developers that would be also
a pretty heavily favored contender you I
think there's a bigger upfront cost to
learning how to program in it and
learning how to program well and it but
you don't have those problems with the
garbage collector so I think if you
pulled our engineers you might get about
an even response between those two
languages but you know this I thing is
true in most projects once you start
down a road even if it's Python and
you're building a database or it's
pretty hard to to back out of it so you
know we chose go originally because it's
what was available rust wasn't available
back in 2014 when the project really is
starting got started and go I've been
programming C++ for a long time before
that and that would have been a
reasonable choice at Google where they
had lots of RPC libraries and so forth
in the open source world after Google it
wasn't clear that the C++ libraries were
going to make the job very easy and it
just seemed like there was a huge amount
of complexity like the boost library for
our pcs was you know you look into it
and you almost start to cry it's so big
and so complex and over-engineered and
so go seem like simpler it had very
straightforward libraries that were all
sort of system libraries it turns out
we've replaced many of those with things
like G RPC over the years so not much of
that original architecture remains but
at the time 2014 I think goes
best choice for building a new
distributed system that's interesting up
so what's coming in cockroach TV what's
the future so this is definitely my my
favorite question so you know I think
it's important to think a little bit
about open source and what's changing in
the world you know in the aughts open
source was as it grew as quickly as it
did because it was creating a much more
convenient model for consumption I mean
you know back in the day open source I'd
say that the number one cool aspect of
it was that the code was available you
could do whatever he wanted with it so
is that that real like um Richard
Stallman freedom type thing which still
exists of course but that was back in
the 80s and the 90s that was the really
great thing about open source it was so
different from the closed source models
but in the arts what really started
happening the reason that open source
became the dominant computing paradigm
were engineering software engineering
paradigm is that developers used to have
to go through procurement I mean it for
anyone that doesn't work in a big
company this is like a hideous process
where you're gonna talk to enterprise
software sales reps and there's gonna be
months long legal review and contracts
and you're gonna get and when we do it
when we sell cockroach to these big
companies it's unbelievable but you know
the the way that you had to get all of
your software that you'd had to use to
build whatever new application or
service was to go through this unwieldy
terrible process and once you've got one
of those things you've got these printed
manuals there was no community that you
could ask other like-minded developers
how they solve the problem so is it that
all changed with open-source and that's
what vaulted it into being the dominant
paradigm but now things are changing
again as they do write all these
ecosystems change and they seem to be
changing faster every year now the
consumption model is moving to services
so people it's great you could just
download a piece of infrastructure a new
you know developer library and open
source you'd have to learn it no problem
but with something like infrastructure
like a database you then have to set up
the monitoring in the deployment but day
2 operations in the amount
of cost related to that is actually
pretty excessive and even as a developer
running it locally and sort of maybe a
sort of pre-production environment
there's a lot of overhead to learn those
things and what Amazon of course is
discovered is that providing
infrastructure as a service is a pretty
big win-win the people are willing to
pay for it and the total cost of
ownership and that's certainly the time
to value like how quickly can you create
something using AWS and all of the
services they provide the answer is much
more quickly than when you had to
download the open source and learn how
to run it yourself and run it in your
environment so it's it's a big step
forward and it's putting a lot of
pressure on open source in the open
source model you know what we have to
think of when we're building a database
is what's the you know there's kind of
two sides to the equation one is what do
we have to do to make the fortune 500
customers happy and then what do we have
to do to make make it so that developers
find cockroach's the easiest most
frictionless database to you know
especially get started with and this is
really important to look at what MongoDB
has done and done very well you know
they they made developers lives easier
and so that's that's something that
we're trying to replicate in our own way
we're obviously not going to get rid of
sequel that's a big part of what
cockroach is but we do need to make
developers lives easier in order to
really solve for that a huge audience of
developers out there that every time
they start a new project they're
thinking about you know what what's the
infrastructure I'm gonna use to make
this thing work and what we're realizing
is okay the average developer out there
especially one that's in a smaller
company but even ones that are big
companies on teens that are doing new
projects they're looking not so much at
databases they have to run themselves
anymore they definitely want services
and I think what's really wrong with the
Amazon model of services I mean there's
Amazon's is other things wrong with it
but the thing that I think's wrong with
it is that it's actually still pretty
heavyweight to get a relational database
and cockroach's than anybody right now
we have a database as a service and it
looks like RDS or like Aurora in terms
of how you provision you know how big
the nodes are how many nodes you want
and it's
actually fairly expensive if you're just
trying to create a hobby project or
something like that you know even the
cheapest RDS is not something that Evan
wants to put the credit card down month
after month for so I think what we're
really looking at for our future is how
do we bring cockroach into the cloud in
a way that creates the next consumption
model which to my mind is to make
relational databases a truly serverless
in the sense that you no longer have to
say I want this many nodes with you know
these kinds of CPUs in this much memory
I need them to be in US East and EU West
like we don't want developers have to
make any of those choices nor do we want
them not to pay for full full VMs what
we'd like to do is make it so that what
you get is just a cockroach cluster and
that cockroach cluster is free and in
fact it's perpetually free so you'll be
able to get a perpetually free
relational database that can scale up to
pretty decent resource utilization
thresholds and still be free so let's
say that's you know somewhere between a
hundred thousand and a million requests
per day and you know it can burst up to
pretty hefty amounts so it's a nice
database it's certainly for any kind of
hackathon or hobby project or academic
coursework or anything like that this is
one that you can rely on is always going
to be free kind of like a nice than
niceness that Gmail brought to the email
landscape back in 2003 versus Yahoo Mail
and hotmail and those other ones we even
think that you should be able to get
these things in such a frictionless
fashion that you don't have to log in to
get it you can just create a relational
database anonymously and so to make that
all possible we have to virtualize
cockroach and the big realization here
is that when you take even this sort of
smallest size VM you know in it doesn't
necessarily run the database that well
but even when even what it does do is
much more than the average project needs
or you know if you're just doing a
little bit of an evaluation or a test
you're developing something or it's just
a little thing that you standing up that
you know some of your friends are
hitting or you're just doing a hobby
project those kinds of things don't
require the literally billions of
requests a day that
even a small VM can can handle so it's
really about realizing okay for every VM
that's created for one of these hobby
projects there's lots of wasted cycles
so we can virtualize that then we can
actually lower the unit economics and
give you know allow databases to be
truly free as Services you know up to
some resource utilization threshold so
that's that's a that's a really cool
project to be working on because you
know we we get this really
pie-in-the-sky opportunity to do
something that actually moves the ball
forward in terms of how easy it is for
developers to get what they're trying to
get done and you know relational
databases are at the heart of most
applications around the world so it's a
it seems like a big opportunity yeah it
seems that seems like a very interesting
way to go about it well with that I'd
like to wrap up Spencer it's been great
having you on the show and talking about
cockroach TB thank you for coming here
it's my pleasure
this is Akshay Macaulay for software
engineering radio thank you for
listening thanks for listening the SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by Archer police software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at SE -
radio net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of se radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening